LeRoy Hodges Papers, 1908-1942 WLU Coll. 0162
Special Collections and Archives, Washington and Lee University
Special Collections and Archives, James G. Leyburn Library, Washington and Lee University
LeRoy Hodges Papers 1908-1942
Special Collections and Archives, James G. Leyburn Library, Washington and Lee University
WLU Coll. 0162
This collection was a gift of LeRoy Hodges, Jr., 1948-1952.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
1888 12 July. Born in Tarboro, North Carolina
1906-1910 Attended Washington and Lee
1911 Married Almeria Orr Hill
1911-1916 Various positions as economist, teacher
1916-1918 Secretary, Virginia Commission on Economy and Efficiency
1918-1922 Aide and director of budget for Govenor Westmoreland Davis
1920-1926 President, State Prison Board (member 1930- 37)
1922-1926 Director of budget (Govenor E. Lee Trinkle)
1924-1937 Managing director, Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. Continued as State Ordance Officer, Virginia National Guard
1937-1938 Director of Federal Old-Age Benefits, Social Security Board
1938-1941 State Comptroller and chair, State Compensation Board (Governor James H. Price)
1941-1942 Served with Army Ordance Office, War Department
1944 18 December, died of leukemia.
See also Who Was Who in America, 1943-1950, various resumes and biographical articles in the collection (box 1).
Scope and Content Information
The collection covers nearly all phases of Hodges' career as economist and public official, from 1908 until 1942, when he retired from the Army Ordnance office. Early materials include reports on Southern agriculture and immigration for various agencies. Hodges' first efforts to reform and streamline Virginia state government may be seen in the minutes and papers of the Virginia Commission on Economy and Efficiency. There is considerable correspondence from his service as aide and director of the Budget under Governors Davis and Trinkle. In 1924, Hodges became the first managing director of the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce; his activities reflected in the official and unofficial correspondence, included development of trade relations with Great Britain and other countries and the creation of the "Five-Five" (later "All Virginia") program designed to enhance the state's internal economy, efficiency, and sense of civic pride. Also included are the Chamber of Commerce's publications and numerous addresses by Hodges on trade and economic issues. During this period Hodges continued to participate in the State Prison Board (he served as the president) and as Colonel in the Virginia National Guard; the collection contains his "Ordnance Notes" and other papers relating to aspects of ordnance and defense preparation in the period between the wars. Hodges' office files as Comptroller include reports, addresses, proposals, and organizations requesting him to speak. A small amount of material concerns his brief service during World War II with the War Department, which was cut short by illness.
Col. Hodges' correspondents include economists, government officials, businessmen, and other prominent figures in Petersburg and Richmond. Among the names represented are W. Jett Lauck, James H. Price, Gordon Bohannon, Junius P. Fishburn, Francis P. Miller, Robert H. Tucker (Prof. Of Economics at Washington and Lee), members of the "Virginia Musketeers" (a group of businessmen and officials in the Richmond area), John W. Davis and Lady Astor.
The collection is of interest to students of reform and government efficiency movements in Virginia politics as well as students of Virginia economic history and army ordnance.
Organization
The collection was processed before 1981, but was still in disorder when cataloged in 1984. It was clear that the original organizational principle reflected the stages of Hodges' career, and the revised order of series reflected this. Ignore original file folder numbering.
Contents List
- Personal papers 1906-1941 (Box 1)
  Genealogies, certificates, resumes, biographical articles; account books; miscellaneous correspondence, 1910-1917.
- Papers and reports 1908-1941 (Box 2 & 3)
  Case studies and articles on Southern agriculture, immigration, various community economies.
- Correspondence 1911-1922 (Box 4-8)
  Principally official and some personal correspondence relating to service as aide to Governor and as private consultant. Includes economic-industrial survey of Petersburg, Virginia and related material on municipal administrations. Correspondents: Governor William H. Mann. W. Jett Lauck
- Virginia Committee on Economy and Efficiency Correspondence 1917-1918 (Box 9-10)
  Correspondence with members, minutes, reports, correspondence with state purchasing agencies.
- Director of the Budget 1922-1924 (Box 11-12)
  Correspondence and reports regarding budgeting and state purchasing procedures
- State Penitentiary Board 1922-1925 (Box 13)
  Reports, correspondence with suppliers.
- Army Ordnance 1923-1940 (Box 14-20)
  Correspondence re Post-War Ordnance(1923); correspondence (including Virginia National Guard and Army Ordnance Association); army courses, 1933-1940; army corps, 1931-1935; "Ordnance Notes" (1931-1936) for National Guard.
- Virginia State Chamber of Commerce 1924-1937 (Box 21-28)
  Correspondence with businessmen, foreign diplomats, state officials concerning development of trade, efficiency of state government, British-American relations; publications of the Chamber of Commerce; Hodges' addresses on state history, economic planning, tourism, trade, etc.; rules, rosters, and correspondence re Virginia Musketeers, group of Virginia businessmen and officials. Correspondents: W. Jett Lauck, Robert H. Tucker, J. Gordon Bohannon, Junius Fishburn, John W. Davis, Leander McCormick-Goodhart, British-American Foundation.
  Also: 2 TLS from Lady Astor and telegram from Richard E. Byrd (Virginia Musketeers-Honorary)
- Social Security Board 1937-1938, Reports, correspondence (Box 29-30)
- Comptroller 1938-1941 (Box 31-47)
  Official and unofficial correspondence concerning speaking engagements, ordnance and planning, taxation (poll and capitation tax), aid to Great Britain, budgeting, trade, governmental reform under Governor Price. Correspondents: J. Gordon Bohannon, W. Jett Lauck, Douglas S. Freeman, Francis P. Miller, Robert H. Tucker, Virginia Policy Committee ("Program of Progress", 1940), Army Ordnance Association, Governor James H. Price.
- War Department 1941-1942 (Box 48)
  Correspondence re army ordnance
- Photographs 1908-1930's (Box 49-50)
  Photographs of Hodges, family, state institutions, Virginia sights, army camps, foreign travel, etc. (see also oversize MSS. drawer)